The final section of this chapter deals with the clinical characteristics of neoplasia.
And the idea here is that once you go through the sequence of carcinogenesis and tumor progression,
eventually the patients will present with certain important clinical characteristics,
and so that's what we want to discuss here.
Now, we're not going to discuss specific characteristics for each individual tumor,
but we're going to discuss some general concepts that you need to have concerning neoplasia
and how it might present clinically.
So obviously, we know that neoplasia can be divided into benign and malignant.
So there are benign tumors and there are malignant tumors.
Generally speaking, benign tumors are going to be slow-growing.
The patient may give a history of having a mass that has grown slowly over many years, for example.
Another characteristic is that the tumor will be well-circumscribed,
and that would be where you would examine the tumor clinically,
and it's clearly distinct and separate from the adjacent tissue in which it's growing.
So, for example, a patient has a breast mass,
and the breast mass is clearly distinct and separate from the remainder of the breast tissue.
And so that's basically what we mean by distinct here.
And finally, it's mobile.
And what does mobile mean?
It means that if you take the mass and try to move it around,
for example, if it was a breast mass, and you try to move it around,
it's easy to move the mass around.
And what does that tell you?
That tells you that the mass is not invading into local tissues,
it's not attaching itself, for example, to the chest wall in the case of the breast.
And so these are some classic clinical features that we would expect in benign tumors.
In contrast, malignant tumors would have the following characteristics.
Malignant tumors are usually rapidly growing.
The patient usually gives a history of a tumor that's grown within a year or grown sometimes within months.
They're poorly circumscribed.
You try to sort of get your hand around the tumor, for example, if it's a breast cancer,
and you can't really separate it from the adjacent surrounding normal breast tissue.
It infiltrates into local tissues, and it's fixed to surrounding structures.
It's not mobile, but instead it's attached, for example, to the chest wall in the case of breast cancer.
And so these are some classic clinical features concerning benign and malignant tumors.
It should be noted, however, that sometimes a benign tumor can have malignant characteristics,
and sometimes a malignant tumor can have benign characteristics.
And so these clinical features are simply screening tests.
The only way to make an absolute diagnosis of cancer is biopsy or excision.
Otherwise stated, it's the pathologist who makes the final determination of cancer.
The only way, again, to make an absolute certain diagnosis of cancer is that the tissue must be biopsied or it must be excised.
And so that's an important principle to bear in mind, and that will come into play later when we have some discussions about screening tests as well.
Now, what are some of the histologic features of cancer?
If cancer is going to be determined on biopsy by looking at the cells under the microscope and clearly calling them malignant,
then we need to understand the histologic features of cancer as well.
Now, generally, when we think about benign tumors, they look very similar to the tissue in which they're growing.
For example, the benign tumors usually have an organized growth.
The nuclei will be uniform.
The nuclear to cytoplasmic ratio will be low.
What does that mean?
It means there will be a lot of cytoplasm in the cell and maybe a small nucleus.
That gives you a low nuclear to cytoplasmic ratio.
There will be minimal mitotic activity, a lack of invasion, and this tumor will have no metastatic potential,
meaning that the tumor will not have the ability to spread outside of that particular organ in that patient or in any other patient.
All right?
And so that's how we understand no metastatic potential.
And, again, this word potential is important because what we do is when we see,
when a biopsy is performed and I see a certain pattern and I call that, let's say, for example,
I call that a benign tumor, like in the breast, I call that a fibroadenoma,
I know that fibroadenomas don't metastasize historically in all the patients that have had fibroadenoma.
And that's what makes it benign.
And so it has no metastatic potential in the patient who's now developed a fibroadenoma as well.
So those are some histologic features of benign tumors.
The histologic features of malignant tumors are as follows.
It's usually poorly differentiated, and I say usually because it doesn't always have to be.
It'll have disorganized growth where it doesn't really look like the tissue in which it's growing.
There'll be nuclear pleomorphism.
Some of the nuclei will be big and some of the nuclei will be small.
There'll be hyperchromasia.
The nuclei will be very dark blue.
There'll be a high nuclear to cytoplasmic ratio.
So if this is the cell, most of the cell will be comprised of nucleus.
And what does that indicate?
That indicates that the cell is very active and that the nucleus is completely open
and is rapidly transcribing genes, etc.
There'll be a high mitotic activity, indicating that the cells are rapidly dividing.
And there'll be invasion into local structures.
And so these are some of the histologic hallmarks that help us to classify a tumor as benign or malignant.
Now, here's an example that I've placed in your text to highlight some of these principles.
And we're basically comparing and contrasting.
So this picture on the left, this is an example of a follicular adenoma of the thyroid.
Now, a follicular adenoma of the thyroid is a benign tumor.
And when you look at the tumor, it shows many of the characteristics that we would expect to see in a benign tumor.
For example, here we can clearly see that these cells, by the way, the entire picture here,
this entire picture that I'm squaring away represents the tumor.
So here we can clearly see that the cells are organizing themselves in little round spaces,
as you would expect to see within the thyroid.
Remember that the thyroid makes follicles, and the follicles are lined by follicular cells.
And often in the center of the follicle, you see colloid.
And you can clearly see some pink colloid in the center of these round nests of cells.
In addition, you can see that the nuclei are sort of regular.
All the cells sort of have round, similar-looking nuclei.
You don't really see any mitotic activity.
The cells don't have a very high N-to-C ratio.
In fact, when you look at the nuclear-to-cytoplasmic ratio,
you can clearly see that if this is a cell here, the nucleus is small,
and there's a lot of cytoplasm above it.
So these are all features that we would expect to see in a benign tumor.
And indeed, on the left, we have this benign thyroid tumor, i.e. a follicular adenoma.
Now, on the right, what I've exhibited here is something called anaplastic carcinoma of the thyroid.
Now, when you look at this tumor, you can tell that clearly it's not making any nice round spaces with colloid in the middle.
You can see that the cells are larger than the cells on the left.
You can see that there's mitotic activity.
This is a mitotic figure here.
You can see that the nuclei are big, and you can see that they take up most of the cell.
And so all of these are features of histologic features of a malignant tumor.
Now, it's important to note, however, that, again, benign tumors can sometimes have malignant features,
and malignant tumors can sometimes have benign features.
So what is the absolute distinguishing feature between benign and malignant?
And this is what examiners like you to know.
The absolute distinguishing feature between benign and malignant is metastatic potential.
Benign tumors do not have metastatic potential.
Malignant tumors have metastatic potential.
So this is a very important take-home point because it's the absolute distinction between benign and malignant tumors.
One important clinically useful test in this context of neoplasia is immunohistochemistry.
And the way we use immunohistochemistry depends on the circumstance that we're challenged with.
But let me just give you a couple simple examples.
Let's pretend that I have a very poorly differentiated cancer.
What does poorly differentiated mean?
It looks nothing like any normal tissue.
So the patient has a mass.
They do a biopsy.
And when I get the biopsy, I see that the cells are poorly differentiated.
They don't look like anything that we're used to seeing.
And so when I see those cells, in the back of my mind, I begin to think,
huh, is this carcinoma?
Meaning, is it epithelial?
Well, is it lymphoma, i.e., are the cells lymphocytes?
Is it sarcoma, i.e., are the cells derived from mesenchyme?
Are they some sort of connective tissue cell?
Or is it melanoma, for example?
And I start with a very broad differential diagnosis because these are all my common subtypes of cancer.
Now, I can look at the cells and try to use morphology to help me to determine what cell type I'm dealing with.
But another useful technique to determine the type of cell is called immunohistochemistry.
The idea here is that we take an antibody against a particular target,
and we label that antibody with a brown stain, and then we place that antibody on the cells.
And if the antibody binds the cells, then it helps us to identify particular proteins
that might help us to subclassify the cell type.
And it's important to be familiar with this because, of course, it's useful clinically.
And also examiners like to go after it because it really draws in some of the basic principles of histology.
So this is a great way to sort of test your histology.
Now, let me remind you that cells have a cytoskeleton,
and the cytoskeleton contains filaments, and one of those filaments is the intermediate filaments.
One subtype of filament of the cytoskeleton is the intermediate filament.
Now, it so happens that the intermediate filaments, they vary depending on the type of cell that you're dealing with.
So, for example, if we're dealing with an epithelial cell,
and we can say that all epithelial cells, the intermediate filament that makes them up is keratin.
So let's say that I have a tumor, and I can't recognize whether the tumor cells are epithelial or something else,
and I wanted to prove that they're epithelial.
Well, I could do an immunohistochemical stain for keratin,
and if the cells are keratin positive, that would indicate that I'm dealing with a carcinoma.
Because, remember, carcinoma is the name that we use for malignant epithelial tumors.
All right, let's play it another way.
Let's pretend that I've got this tumor, and I do an immunohistochemical stain,
and I see that the cells are positive for vimentin.
Well, vimentin is an intermediate filament that is present within mesenchymal cells, i.e., connective tissue cells.
And so if I have vimentin positivity, one of the things that I could deduce is that I'm dealing with a sarcoma,
because I've got a malignant tumor, obviously I can't recognize it, the cells are poorly differentiated,
and it's vimentin positive.
Playing along the same lines, let's say that the cells are desmond positive,
that would indicate that I'm dealing with muscle cells.
If they're GFAP positive, that would indicate that I'm dealing with neural glial cells.
And if they're neurofilament positive, that would indicate that I'm dealing with neurons.
So these intermediate filaments are very high yield, because it goes back to histology,
and because we use these clinically, it's not uncommon for us to order a battery of immunohistochemical stains
when we're trying to subclassify tumor.
So you do need to be familiar with this.
Now, obviously I'm painting very broad strokes and highlighting some general principles.
There are some exceptions to these rules, but I think for your purposes, this is what you need to understand.
Another way that we could play the game is that, let's say we have a tumor,
and we know that it's a carcinoma, it's making glands,
and we're concerned about whether it might be from the prostate or it might be from another organ.
Well, we could do an immunohistochemical stain for PSA,
and if the cells are PSA positive, that would suggest that we're dealing with a prostate cancer.
Similarly with breast.
You know, if a woman has a metastatic cancer in the lung,
and I'm worried about where that tumor came from,
one potential way of determining that would be to do an estrogen receptor stain,
and if the estrogen receptor is expressed in those cells,
it's possible that I'm dealing with a breast cancer,
because estrogen receptor is commonly seen in breast carcinoma.
Thyroglobulin would help me to identify a thyroid cancer.
Chromogranin would help me to identify neuroendocrine carcinomas.
And I would say from my personal experience that chromogranin is a relatively high-yield stain to be familiar with.
It's commonly tested by examiners.
The most well-differentiated and sort of best type of neuroendocrine cancer that you can get
is called a carcinoid tumor,
and the worst and most poorly differentiated neuroendocrine tumor that can develop is a small cell carcinoma.
And so this is sort of a spectrum of tumors that arise from neuroendocrine cells.
It is important to understand that both small cell carcinoma and carcinoid tumors
are sort of derived from the same cell type, i.e. neuroendocrine cells,
and it is very high-yield to know that chromogranin is expressed in neuroendocrine cells.
And then finally, the last of the stains I've listed here is S100,
and S100 is useful for many things, but it's particularly useful to mark melanoma.
So, you know, the way that examiners like to play the game with immunohistochemical stains
is that they might say to you that there's a tumor and a biopsy is performed,
and the pathologist sends you a report saying that he sees or she sees keratin-positive cells.
So they would then ask you, what type of tumor are you dealing with?
And the answers could, you know, the choices could be A, carcinoma, B, melanoma, C, lymphoma, D, sarcoma,
and obviously because it's keratin-positive, that would indicate epithelium,
which would then indicate that you have a carcinoma.
So I hope that I've made that clear because it is a relatively high-yield topic.
Here's a picture of an immunohistochemical stain just to let you know what one looks like.
Basically, this brown staining indicates that the cells are reacting
with the particular antibody that we've introduced in this test.
Now, another way by which we can classify tumors
and follow the treatment and response of tumors are serum tumor markers.
What are serum tumor markers?
These are proteins that are released by the tumor.
They are released, obviously, into the serum.
Now, these serum tumor markers can be useful in three circumstances.
Some serum tumor markers are useful as a screening test.
For example, PSA is a protein that's released by prostate cancer,
and it gets released into the blood, and we can then detect it in the blood,
and so it's useful as a screening test.
That would be one use of a serum tumor marker.
Another use of serum tumor markers is to monitor response to treatment.
For example, patient has a prostate cancer.
The PSA is 15.
The surgeon goes in and removes the prostate cancer and removes the prostate along with the cancer,
and after removing the prostate along with the cancer,
we would expect the PSA to drop to near zero.
And so this would be a way by which we would monitor response to treatment.
And then let's say that the patient comes back in, I don't know, two years later,
and when they come back in two years later, they have bone pain.
Well, if we did a PSA and the PSA was now high, that would help to prove that perhaps the patient has a recurrence.
And so these are some of the uses for serum tumor markers.
I want to remind you that when it's used for screening,
elevated serum levels still require a tissue biopsy for diagnosis.
I think I've already hammered home this point.
You cannot make a diagnosis of cancer without a tissue biopsy.
And so even if a patient has a super high PSA, let's say, you know, some crazy number like 3-400,
that still would require a tissue biopsy before a diagnosis of carcinoma can be made.
And so, for example, if I asked you a question where I said patient comes in for screening
and a PSA is performed and the PSA is markedly elevated, what's the next step?
A surgery, B biopsy, CDE, etc.
The answer would be that you still need to biopsy the site and prove that it is tumor that is indeed causing that elevated PSA.
And that's because other things can elevate the PSA as well, not only cancer.
Now, once a patient has a cancer and we've made the diagnosis of cancer,
the next thing that the pathologist does, which is important for prognosis, is to grade the cancer.
And what does grading of cancer involve?
It involves asking the question, does the tumor look like the tissue in which it's growing?
So the more the tumor looks like the parent tissue in which it's growing, the better differentiated it would be.
And so, if it resembles the parent tissue, as I've stated here, it's well differentiated.
And if it does not resemble the parent tissue, we call that poorly differentiated.
How do we determine differentiation?
Well, we look at the architecture of the cells and ask, does the architecture resemble the normal architecture of that tissue?
And then we also look at the nuclear features, like, for example, the mitotic activity.
Again, as I've mentioned, grading is important for determining prognosis.
The better differentiated a tumor is, or a cancer is, the better the prognosis.
So a well-differentiated cancer has a good prognosis.
A poorly differentiated cancer has a poor prognosis.
Another important feature of cancer that we need to be familiar with on a clinical level is staging.
And staging basically asks the question, how far has the cancer grown?
So what's its size or depth of invasion?
And how far has the cancer spread?
So it's based on two things, size and spread of the cancer.
Now, this is the key prognostic factor.
It is the number one prognostic factor.
It is more important than grade.
And the final staging is really determined after resection of the tumor.
So clinically, we can stage a patient.
We can try to determine what we think the clinical staging would be based on our clinical exam.
However, the true final staging is based on resection of the tumor.
When the tumor is removed and the pathologist analyzes the tissue, they then provide a final pathologic staging for the cancer.
Now, what system do we use for staging?
It's called the TNM system.
It looks at three key factors.
It looks at the tumor and asks the question, how big is the tumor or how deep has the tumor invaded?
Generally speaking, tumor size is important in solid organs.
And generally speaking, tumor depth is important in organs that are tubular.
So, for example, the bowel, the depth of invasion is important in the bowel.
Whereas in the breast, size is important because it's a more solid organ.
So that's the T part of the TNM staging.
The N in the TNM refers to the spread to regional lymph nodes.
This is the second most important prognostic factor.
And the M refers to distant metastasis, i.e. away from the regional lymph nodes.
And this is the single most important prognostic factor.
Metastasis is the single most important prognostic factor in the TNM staging system.
And you do need to be aware of that as well.
And so that really closes off our discussion of neoplasia.
Again, we've just laid out some very general principles.
Much of this is going to be repeated as we cover systems.
But it's nice to have a little bit of a framework as we move forward.
And that was the goal of this lecture.